Hey guys, Shandide welcome back. And
till now we have seen how schedule
should scheduleuler works internally,
how in a single application how to
implement scheduleuler like fixed rate,
fixed delay. We have already seen that.
Now before we move to distributeduling
part, I will also cover like how
interviewer
reach till that point. So interview
start from common pitfalls which happens
in you can say that day-to-day
shoulduling which we are doing in an
application which while we are
implementing. So it starts from there
ultimately it end up till the
distributed shoulduling part. Okay. So
let's start without wasting any time
because this is very important topic and
I'll try to cover as many pitfalls as
possible.
So the first pitfall is we have already
seen the chron job. So chron job and
time zone issue pitfall. So the problem
is that when we are using this chron job
let's say at the rate scheduled chron is
this what is this one this is second
minute r and it's like any value. So it
means like every day 9:00 a.m. we want
to run this scheduleuler job. That's
what it means every day at 9:00 a.m. But
the question is which time zone? because
we haven't defined what if your server
is running in UTC and your user is
present into IST. Okay, so this chronops
runs at 9:00 a.m. UTC.
So it's always by default runs picks the
server time zone.
So like uh if your user is in
IST time zone then 9:00 a.m. UTC is your
2:30 p.m. IST. Okay. So if you have
certain uh job to send morning
notification that morning morning
notification user received in afternoon
2:30 p.m. Indian standard time. Okay.
Why? Because your server is running in
UTC and you haven't defined anything. So
it solution is with chron's job always
specifically use the zone.
Okay. So that's very important and the
first pitfall solution.
Second is missing at the rate
transactional.
Uh I would say that many engineers
already know this one but it's good to
cover this. So now let's say uh this is
our scheduleuler job and which is first
fetch
fetch all the record. Now for each
record it is updating something
updating let's say table one and a table
two.
And what if while updating the table two
certain exception comes but in the table
one the value is updated properly.
Okay. So the same thing let's say you
are working on subscription 101 there
are so many subscription you are working
on 101 status is updated properly
expired but enrollment deletion got
failed. So roll back is not happen for
subscription table status column. Hence
data is now in inconsistent state and we
know the solution that we need to put at
the rate transactional here. So you can
give transaction at class level. Okay.
So that by default it would be applied
to all public methods or if you want on
any specific method you can also write
it on a specific method. So we have
already covered those part. So right the
third pitfall
is fetching huge data. the memory issue.
What is this problem? [clears throat] So
now we have a transactional. Okay, well
and good. This query
in schedule shoulder could be an issue.
Why? Because schedule should
scheduleuler is like hey find by expiry
date before this time.
So it's possible that you are fetching
so many records. It's possible in
scheduulers when you are dealing with a
scheduulers and you do a get call to
work on certain data it's possible that
your query is fetching so many records
and let's say in the example which I'm
taking if 85,000 records this query is
fetching and each record is 10 KB then
it's around 850 MB of data just from
this query alone and let's say it's all
hypothetical If JVM heap is 512 MB the
result you will get is out of memory
Java heap space and what will happen is
the next time scheduleuler run the same
issue. So it will always fail always.
Okay. So
fetching huge data is a very big pitfall
you can say that when you're dealing
with scheduulers and its solution is
batch processing. So here how I
converted this uh code change is like
while true. Okay so continue and here
now in each query I am fetching top
1,000 records itself. Okay. So the query
I have modified with limit thousand. So
what it will do is it will fetch the top
1,000 records only. Okay. And here if
you see also I have added a status that
not in expired because see earlier you
were running the query only one time. So
there is no point of like let's say that
give me the all the data
expired which are not in expired.
Okay but date has passed through.
So fetch me all the data. So you are
running it only one time. Now
in the batch processing the major thing
we have to uh take note of it is that
you are running in a while loop
continuously because you have to fetch
all the records. You are keep on
fetching thousand thousand records.
Okay. So you have to make sure that you
don't end up in infinite loop because
see this is very critical. You are
within a while true loop. Okay. So you
should not end up in infinite looping.
So that's where I am focusing more here
is that have a proper query
double check your query that it do not
end up in infinite loop. Okay. So here
when I f the top thousand records what I
am doing is I change their status to
expired. So that's where I'm just
checking and status is not in expired so
that I always get new records which I
have to work on and only 1,000.
Okay.
So this is another solution for the
pitfall is that uh when you have
working with huge data don't just hit
one query follow the batch processing
and while following the batch processing
make sure
you have you don't end up in infinite
loop and I told you that here whatever
the status you are updating depending
upon your business logic your query
should be such that
it excludes those are already executed.
Okay.
So now what would happen? Now I am
fetching thousand record at a time. So
how many times it will run? Batch
one,000 records. Batch two,000 records.
Similarly batch 85,000
records. So all 85,000
records will get processed into 85 batch
small chunks. Now each 1,000 record is
of now 10 MB. Okay. So earlier we have
1850 MB in one shot. Now each batch is
of only 10 MB and once the work is
completed GC can reclaim this memory.
Okay. So once the work is completed it
they are free to go. They are free uh
garbage collector is free to remove them
from the heap. Similarly now for bash
two we are working in small small
chunks. Okay. So this is batch
processing.
Clear but there is a problem with
memory leak here itself in the batch
processing. So interer will say you that
hey even after batch processing your
memory issue will not fix. Why?
It's because
the problem is
we have put at the rate transactional at
top of this or you can say that even if
not here if you have add the rate
transactional
at very very top level. So what would
happen? So even though you are running
multiple batch batch one batch two batch
85 but all of these batches are part of
only one transactional
one transaction and because of this if
you can recall in a spring boot I have
told you about the first level caching
okay so that's where the problem is
So everything is running under one big
add the rate transactional. All 85 batch
the small small batch are part of one
transaction only. And in JPA we have
something called persistence context
which maintains or you can say that
which is helpful in maintaining the
first level cache.
And this persistence context maintains
the reference of all entities loaded
during the transaction. And since this
is maintaining the reference when you
are saying that garbage collector can
reclaim memory will it? No. Because
persistence context is maintaining the
reference. So with batch one 10 MB batch
2 so it's become keep on growing 10 MB
plus 10 MB. So this memory will keep on
growing as you run the batch.
Okay. So memory issue ultimately you can
say that uh delayed but it will
eventually come because of first level
cache.
So also I want to uh just take couple of
minutes more that when you are dealing
with normal spring boot application rest
API HTTP request. Okay then by default
open session in view is enabled.
In that way what happen is when the
request comes
okay
at that time itself for each request
persistence context is created okay so
no matter if you have one transaction
two transaction three transaction
for each request one persistence context
is created. So when the filter comes it
create a new persistence context object
then it goes to a controller service
repository and no matter how many
transactions you create okay within this
request itself all will share the one
persistence context okay
you can anyway disable it so in
application.properties properties you
can do JPA spring.jpa.open-
iny- view equals to false and when you
make it false what happen is the
persistence context
life is only restricted to your
transaction scope by default it's for
each request when request enters and the
when before the request goes. So it have
persistence context life cycle is this.
But if you don't want you want for each
transaction you can make open - in- view
equals to false. Now your persistence
context will be created only when
transaction is created.
Okay. So if you create let's say this is
transaction one. If you create
transaction two for that also new
persistence context will be created.
Okay. And now in scheduleuler there is
no HTTP request. Okay. So there is no
concept of you can say that open session
in view enabled. You can't enable it. So
by default for scheduleulers you can say
that it's always
false. So for each transaction
a new persistence context is created.
Okay. So this is uh just a heads up on
the first level caching part.
Now we know the solution. What to do?
The solution here is that
for each batch we have batch one, batch
two, batch 85. Here I am fetching 1,000
records. Here I am fetching 1,000
records.
For each batch we can have a transaction
new transaction
because
when
for each batch we have a transaction and
this will finish its job. Ultimately the
first level catch you can say that its
uh life is scope its scope of life is
just for this transaction only for this
batch. Once this is completed the
persistence context will destroy it and
the reference is also destroyed in the
first level cache persistence context
then it is eligible for GC GC will
remove it. Okay. So that's what I have
done here. So I have if you see I have
removed the add the transaction from
here. Okay. And all the logic I have
just created another class at the rate
service annotated with and all the logic
for the batch. Okay, fetch 1 th00and
records and then for each record change
it to expired and delete the enrollment
and keep on running. Okay, all for
thousand records here I'm keep on
running. So this is one batch
processing. So I have annotated with at
the rate transitional.
Okay. And from the parent I am just
iterating the while loop. So for batch
one it will run then batch two then
batch three then batch four and for each
batch I am having at the rate
transaction
make sense
so that also problem is resolved.
Now we have something called another
pitfall is exception handling. So this
is you can say that u
very not tricky but like different
solution with by different engineers you
can say that or like different person
different way of handling the exception
in case of scheduleuler. Okay. But I
would tell you that what exception
handling should have
in case of scheduleuler the best
exception handling the thing is that see
till now what we have done is batch
[snorts] one batch 2 batch 85. Okay
multiple because all 85,000 records we
are not processing in a single time. We
are running in batches of,000,000
records
and this is all one scheduleuler job.
So what is the best exception handling
could be? The best exception handling
could be that hey if one job failed here
if one job failed here it should not
fail all thousand.
Okay
and if one batch failed it should not
fail all the other batches.
Okay. So that's what you can say that
one bad subscription because here in
this example I am just giving you a
subscription example. So we have let's
say working on thousand subscription. So
one bad subscription
the entire batch fails. If the problem
is generally whatever the design we have
currently. So in this design consider
that if any problem comes here so
currently UF has thousand record this
list has thousand records. Okay. You are
iterating over thousand. Okay, if any
issue comes, you will come out of this
for loop. Okay, so one bad subscription,
entire batch fails. And similarly
here if one batch got failed, if one
batch got failed, somehow you will come
out of this while loop. So entire whole
scheduleuler failed. No other batch will
run. And also we haven't put any logging
itself. If anything fails in
scheduleuler how you will find out
ultimately.
So now let's handle all these three
scenario. First one bad subscription
entire batch fail scenario.
So this is our batch for which we have
written right process batch fetching the
thousand records and process it. So this
is the failure scenario. Let's say the
subscription 900 is in processing. So we
are in loop for loop uh to out of 1,000
let's say 900 is in processing and while
deleting the enrollment
it throws some DB constraint error let's
say the whole transactions got roll back
in this one so because it is under the
transactional and issue comes here the
whole transaction
rolled back because see even though you
have for 900
subscriptions you have already
successfully updated the status
enrollment but Because of one issue,
the whole 899 already processed is lost.
For 899, you have already successfully
updated the status uh subscription
status and enrollment repo.
Those will be lost to because it is
under at the rate transactional. Even
one failure will come everything will be
rolled back and also out of,000 at 900
you got the error. So the remaining 9001
to,000 that will also never be touched.
You are out of this batch itself.
So how we can improve it is that for
each subscription at record level. So
you can say that this is record handling
for each record I am handling. So for
each out of thousand you got thousand
records here. Now you are iterating over
all the thousands. Now for each one I am
under try catch block. Okay. So I tried
to update it properly but if any
exception comes while processing this
subscription I am having a proper
logging also and proper update of the
status. Why this is important? Okay,
because when the next time you fetch it,
this record should not come because uh
let's say you are not able to uh make
this status expired or you are not able
to delete this enrollment. Okay. So I
have marked the status failed.
Okay. And here in this
I updated that in the query status not
in expired and failed. You know why?
Because see every time in the batch one
till batch 85 I am fetching
top 1,000
okay which status is expired which
status is not in expired this is our
query right not in expired till here
okay but now let's say if on any
particular record you are not able to
change its status okay any issue comes
then next time if you don't if you don't
do this you just log it. Okay. So what
would happen is in the next batch also
this record will come and that record is
you can say that will come with every
batch and it will fail with every batch
itself and it will just keep on logging
itself.
So the best way to handle this scenario
is that for each record-wise if there is
any issue with the record have a proper
status update somewhere either you have
a different table where you are
maintaining the record failure status or
in the same table if you have some
status which is if it is not able to
update properly. So have a proper status
that failed so that at later time you
able to fetch the failure records and
work on it.
So this is one best way to handle record
level failure and also it automatically
handles that if one out of thousand if
one record fails.
Okay, the one thing is you have a proper
information in the DB now that this
record failed. It's not able to process
properly in DB also you have a proper
logger also. Okay. And in the next run
also since you have updated the status
in the next run it will not come and
your remaining
899 job which you have already covered
let's say that will not get rolled back
plus you will be able to complete rest
of the remaining 100 trans subscription
also. So what I mean to say that one bad
subscription will not block your
complete batch processing.
Okay. Now another is one batch failure
whole scheduleuler fails. So till now we
have handled the record level. Now we
can also handle the batch level. So at
this batch
if any issue comes so you are running
multiple batch right here. Batch one
then batch two then batch three. If any
issue comes
then again let's say bash three
while processing throws exception and
while f while while fetching from the DB
let's say here at this point of time
some exception comes what would happen
scheduleuler stops entirely batch one
and batch two are committed so they are
saved so now let's say batch one runs
okay successfully processed now batch
two comes successfully processed
Batch three comes, exception comes here.
Now exception comes here. But your batch
one and batch two in their transaction.
So those are committed properly. Okay.
But no continuation for the remaining
batches. So it will come out of this
exception while loop because some
exception come. So batch three because
of batch three till batch 85 it won't be
able to execute.
So we can handle that. So another way is
that either you can have try catch block
here. Okay. Or
see this is the place where we are
starting the batch work right. So have
this everything into the try cage block
also. And how your business logic say
that how to handle the batch failure you
can handle it. Currently I'm doing a
proper logging that batch DB failure.
That's all. Let's say if best three
fails okay if something got failed up
its cache block will come it will just
do if you have to put it into some DB or
do a proper logging or alerting you can
do that here okay but ultimately I'm
returning true here okay and it will
proceed the next batch itself
okay so batch level handling is also
proper and also the entire you can have
it like overall scheduleular job. Now
whenever the scheduleuler is starting
have it in a try catch block even though
we have divided into different batches.
Okay, each ba batch we have handled it
but it's always better that
everything should be under try catch but
if anything any issue any exceptions
let's say comes here in the parent it
also should not
like silent silent you can say the
silent failure it should not be silent
failure because if any issue comes and
if you don't alert it properly or don't
log it properly ly it would be missed.
Okay. So this is you can say it's a uh
safety net the parent one. So these are
the three level you can say that record
level safety
batch level safety and overall
scheduleuler level safety. So generally
exception handling in scheduleuler in my
opinion should be handled at this three
layer itself.
Okay.
Now another let's move to the another
pitfall. So let's understand this use
case.
So total expired uh data which we are
processing is 85,000. The same example
we are doing we are making a get call
right to process to fetch the data from
DB. Let's say 85,000 and the batch size
is of a,000 and total number of batches
is 85. This is what we have uh done till
now.
Now every per record what we are doing
is we are making one update subscription
like we are making the status change to
expired and we are deleting the
enrollment one delete enrollment
delete operation and one update
operation.
So with every record we are doing two
operation. So 1,000 records each batch
1,000 record two SQL operation. So 2,000
SQL operation per batch like this we
have 85 batches. So appro 1 lakh 70,000
SQL statement you are doing. So up and
down one SQL statement you can say that
a round trip. So 1 lak 70,000 round
trips you are doing it's like a network
call.
Okay. So consider this as an add-up
latency. So you have to be very very uh
like do a proper analysis of your
latency when you are working with
scheduleuler like how many SQL
operations maximum your batch can do.
Okay. So currently at this example which
we are dealing with and the example
which we have taken around 1 lak 70,000
SQL round trips will happen. Okay. Can
we save it? Yes, we can follow hibernate
batching. Okay. So, internally still
there would be like one lakh 70,000 SQL
execution itself. Okay. So even though
no matter how you have to do still the
number of SQL operation is same for each
record one you have to do update you
have to do delete for record two update
delete like this 85,000
record you have to do update and delete
so we are not reducing the number of
operation what we are reducing is the
number of calls like first Round trip
for update you are making let's say one
round trip for record two you are making
one route trip like this making you are
making one route trip for each and every
operation can we reduce it yes
like batch so in hibernate we have
something called springjpa
hibernate dot jdbc dotbatch size 50 so
what we are saying is that
club 50 operation once and send it in a
single shot.
Okay. And also one more thing is this is
very important order update equals to
true. So why it is important is let's
say without order update what would
happen is let's say currently I'm doing
update subscription then update
enrollment update subscription then
update enrollment. If you are not
allowing hibernate to do reordering, so
it's like
subscription table, enrollment table,
subscription table, enrollment table. So
it will not be able to do proper
grouping. So your batch will not might
not work properly. Okay. So if you need
a proper batching, you need to allow
hibernate that hey you are allowed to do
reordering. So now with this one, it can
reorder. All subscriptions can be
grouped together. All enrollment update
should be grouped together and and as
soon as the batch size become 50. Okay,
it send them together using one JDBC
batch call
and because of this we have a lower CPU
usage and shorter job duration which
ultimately impact our you can say the
latency. We have a job duration very
less
all the network calls we are reducing
actually.
Okay. So hibernate batching can be an
answer if interviewer say that hey can
we improve more.
Okay we have already done improvement
through batch then batch plus
transaction for each batch we are having
a transaction so we improve the memory.
Okay and then further we can improve
through hibernate batching.
Now here if you see that till this point
at all the six points we have done with
the uh like pitfalls which are related
to single instance. Okayuler in a
running in a single instance. So here
till this point everything is clear
because now we are moving it to multiple
instances.
Any doubt in this one? Six pitfalls
please go through again. Batch execution
simple right. Exception handling very
simple three layer we need to uh keep
track of. Uh and uh transaction per
batch uh I think it should be clear.
First level catch I have already told
you that how memory leak happen that why
need transaction per batch persistence.
This is important right? So if you are
dealing with the spring boot APIs right
you will see that even though you have
multiple transaction they are sharing a
persistence context sharing the first
level cache because for each request it
create a persistence context
we can turn it off this is the default
we can turn it off through this
okay so that it will have for each
transaction it will create a first level
cache only but in scheduleuler this is
the default transaction itself because
we don't have any HTTP request itself
Awesome.
So now we have a basic understanding of
all the pitfalls.
Now inter ultimately have taken us to
okay what happen
when we have multiple instances.
Then the problem first he want to listen
is that duplicate execution will happen.
So see you have this scheduleuler job. I
have written this scheduleuler job.
Okay. Whatever we have done now we have
two instances of our job or let's say
our scheduleuler is running two pods pod
one pod two
now at 1:00 a.m. So this is second
minute R at 100 a.m. both
pods will try to execute this job see
both are independent the same code is
deployed here the same code is deployed
here okay so at 1:00 a.m. both will
start executing the code. What would
happen? Both is doing the operation in a
duplicate manner. They both will select
the top thousand like process batch. Now
in the process each for each batch what
they are doing is they select the top
thousand part two will also select the
same thousand. Okay. It will update the
status. It will also update the status
again. While updating the status maybe
putting internally lock but it will
ultimately be released and then it will
also update. It will delete all
enrollment. It will also try to delete
may get exception also because there is
no data to delete. But what I'm trying
to say that we are doing duplicate
execution and consider this is very a
serious problem when you are dealing
with financial data. What if you are job
is to transfer the money or refund and
because of this duplication you end up
refund two times or if it is a debit
operation you end up performing debit
two times. then you have a compliance
issue.
So this duplication issue is very
important and that's where interviewer
is more interested in and more of the
pitfalls is just like 5 10 minute
discussion ultimately this is the major
discussion point when you have a
scheduleuler running in multiple parts
when your application in multiple parts
how you will handle the duplication
the first solution is the pessimistic
lock.
So now here if you see how I am handling
is the same thing. This is my parent
job. This is till now here we have
achieved it like this is for exception
handling I have overall scheduleuler
into track catch block in the while true
I am uh keep on running for each batch.
Okay so you can say that for each batch
I have a transactional
and I have a batch level try catch block
for each batch is fetching the thousand
record. Same thing no change at all till
now and for each thousand record for
each record now I have a safety net okay
and I am handling it
now where we are doing the pessimistic
lock so now this is the place where we
are fetching the thousand records okay I
have changed the query to earlier we
have only limit 100 right I have also
added four update
now what would happen with this that
lock would be acquired on thousand rows
by only one transaction other
transaction will wait for the lock to
release. So even though you have two pod
pod one and pod two both runs at the
same time
now it will acquire like 1,000
transactions top 1,000 transaction it
will acquire the log this will now wait.
Okay. So this would be the runtime
behavior. Begin the transactions.
This is part one. Pod two. Begin the
transaction. Select for update. It will
also run select for update. But only one
would be able to log the thousand rows.
Another will get blocked here. Waiting
for instance once commit. So now the
instance one will process it, commit it,
then it will get unblocked.
So this is the timeline way. Okay. So
log cross it is waiting. It will process
it is waiting. When it do ultimately
comment then it will get the log and
then it will start the process. Okay.
But what would happen it's select for
update
you can say that whatever the logs
[snorts] or whatever the rows it has
updated those rows will not come to this
one because those are already updated.
So you should have a proper query they
not in expired or not in failed so that
when instance 2 is try to fetch
this one all thousand first top thousand
records it already change it to expired
properly.
So when you are running this query not
in expired not in fil those thousand
will not come now. Okay. So it will pick
maybe next 1,000
and when it pick next thousand instance
will might wait.
But this has a very uh important con and
this is where interior says that hey is
this the best we can do. The major
problem is this blocking nature.
It's never recommended that your
scheduleuler job is waiting. It's never
recommended. It's not scalable as other
instances are just blocked by one
instance. So generally there are not two
instances. Uh if you are working in a
big organization you know that there are
hundreds of pots. If your one instance
is working like and like maybe you are
all 100 instances and different
different parts are just waiting. So
it's a wastage of resource happening
and if the instance one won't get
blocked for 1 hour because of some long
running task all other instances also
get blocked for 1 hour.
So go for it only when you have one or
two instance and a small batch or you
want a strict order whenever you have a
strict order that then first this
thousand after that this thousand then
this,000. So here if you see that our
query ordered by
okay so we are following certain order
and always it f top thousand so now we
are following some ordering but if you
have a requirement that you don't
need to process them in order then we
have a better solution which we will
see.
So interview said can we resolve this or
we can can we make it more little bit
efficient? Yes, we can do that. If
strict ordering is not required, then we
can do parallel processing. How we can
do parallel processing? Pessimistic lock
but with skip log feature. But please
note that skip log feature is depend
upon which DB you are using. So all
major DB like MySQL, Postgress, uh they
have they support Oracle they support
this skip block feature. So what this
skip block feature is let's say uh you
have thousand records 1 2 3
1 th00and
now let's say u instance one instance
two instance one has put a lock on this
three and first now instance two when it
tried to take a lock on this three let's
say I have having like top limit three
limit three so three rows top three rows
it need to log. Now let's say instance
one has taken a log. Now instance two
will not wait skip log. So these three
are locked. So it will skip it and move
it to the next three. It will take next
three. So that's what the skip log
feature allow a query to bypass rows
already logged by other transaction.
So instance one take first thousand
instance two take next thousand and it
will go on. So now we are doing parallel
processing. Now instance two is not
waiting for instance one to release it
the first thousand. Okay. Again it's
always like top thousand only. Okay. Our
query is always top thousand.
But if top thousand is logged by
somebody else the second instance will
not wait. it will pick whatever the next
top thousand uh rows it can get. Okay.
So no duplicate, no waiting, parallel
processing which is good for
scalability.
So this is how we do that. The query
earlier we have put for update. Now we
just have like skip log for update skip
log you can add it. The syntax might be
different. Check like whichever DB you
are using. see what is the syntax it
support. Okay. And also the DB does
support a skip log or not. But in my
view all major DBs are supporting a skip
log.
So till now what we have achieved is
even if we have multiple instances
they can process the task in parallel
and in a much efficient manner. But
again one interviewer can ask you that
hey what if
I want so this is my scheduleuler I want
only one instance instance one instance
two instance three I only want one
instance to work on this scheduleuler I
don't even want instance two instance
three and multiple instances to work
even if I have 100 instances out of this
100 only one should work on the
scheduleuler
Rest 99 should do some other work. Okay,
this could be a requirement also company
to company and this is also a very good
you can say that uh distributed
scheduleuler use case when you have 100
instances
and you want only one scheduleuler to
work on it.
How you can do that?
That's where the shedlock comes into the
picture where requirement is only one
instance should run the job. Okay. And
this is very important like you can say
that many companies follow this also
like they want only one scheduleuler or
one instance to focus on the
scheduleuler part. Rest 99 instances if
you have multiple pods focus on some
other task.
Okay.
So the shedlock part is again a big
topic. I'll with diagrams I will try to
go slow and cover everything because
this is very important part of
distributed scheduleuler. So see you in
the next video and please go through all
the pitfalls till now we have covered.
Okay, very important part. Okay guys,
bye.